{"tossups": [{"question": "As a child, this man spoke the South Carolina creole language Gullah. In 1991, this man was at the center of widely viewed Congressional hearings over his alleged use of a can of Coca-Cola to sexually harass Anita Hill. He has since been accused of rarely speaking and visibly falling asleep during oral arguments. For 10 points, name this conservative Supreme Court Justice.", "answer": "Clarence <b><u>Thomas</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This character is portrayed in the 2008 conservative satire film <em>An American Carol</em> by Kelsey Grammer. Kirk Douglas portrayed him in <em>Is Paris Burning?</em>, and his \"last days\" were the subject of a 1986 TV movie in which his most notable portrayer reprised this role. For 10 points, name this commander of the Third Army who was played in a 1970 biopic by George C. Scott.", "answer": "George Smith <b><u>Patton</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "An opera from this country is about a peasant who averts an invasion by leading the Polish army into a forest. This country's nationalist group \"The Mighty Handful\" composed <em>Pictures at</em> <em>an Exhibition</em> and <em>Flight of the Bumblebee</em>. For 10 points, name this home country of Modest Mussorgky (<b>pr. moo-SORG-skee</b>) and Rimsky-Korsakov (<b>pr. RIM-skee-CORE-suh-koff</b>).", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Charles Redheffer's exhibition of one of these devices was undone by a precocious child who noticed the wearing of gear teeth. John Gamgee's attempt to create a device of this kind called the Zeromotor failed because of the energy needed to cool ammonia. For 10 points, name these pseudoscientific devices which were proved impossible by the Second Law of Thermodynamics.", "answer": "<b><u>perpetual motion</u></b> machines", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This event was a planned stunt orchestrated by George Rappelyea and other local business leaders, who correctly predicted that celebrities such as H.L. Mencken, William Jennings Bryan, and Clarence Darrow would flock to Dayton, Tennessee and bring tourist dollars with them. For 10 points, name this 1925 proceeding over the charge of \"teaching evolution.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Scopes</u></b> trial [or <b><u>monkey</u></b> trial]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The <em>William</em> was scuttled by a storm before being subject to this event, which instead targeted the <em>Eleanor</em>, <em>Beaver</em>, and <em>Dartmouth</em>. It began on the saying of the code phrase \"This meeting can do nothing further to save the country\" by Samuel Adams. For 10 points, name this 1773 incident in which the Sons of Liberty dressed as Mohawks and destroyed British goods.", "answer": "<b><u>Boston Tea Party</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The introduction of copper plating caused incidents of this kind named for Spithead and Nore. Fletcher Christian led another event of this kind, which caused a new population to settle on Pitcairn Island and opposed William Bligh. For 10 points, name these events in British history in which the crew of a ship rebelled against the captain, as on the <em>HMS Bounty</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>mutiny</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This position was first held by a man named St. Augustine who is not to be confused with the one who wrote <em>The City of God</em>. This position is currently held by Justin Welby, who succeeded Rowan Williams. For 10 points, name this religious position at the head of the Anglican Church, which is named for the city that was the destination of Chaucer\u2019s pilgrims.", "answer": "<b><u>Archbishop of Canterbury</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man worked under the non-painter Diego Vel\u00e1zquez, who dispatched him from Cuba. This man's forces were nearly routed in La Noche Triste (<b>pr. NOH-chay TREES-tay</b>), and he was aided by the traitor La Malinche (<b>pr. mah-LEEN-chay</b>). For 10 points, name this conqueror of Tenochtitlan (<b>pr. tay-NOK-teet-lon</b>) who defeated Montezuma to claim Mexico for Spain.", "answer": "Hern\u00e1n <b><u>Cort\u00e9s</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This military leader was declared a martyr by Pope Callixtus III, a generation after this saint's capture at Compi\u00e8gne (<b>pr. cahmp-YEN-yuh</b>). Pierre Cauchon (<b>pr. COO-shun</b>) led the court which condemned her to be burned at the stake in 1431 following her relief of the siege of Orl\u00e9ans (pr. <b>OH-lee-ahn</b>). For 10 points, name this teenage French patriot of the Hundred Years War.", "answer": "<b><u>Joan of Arc</u></b> [or <b><u>Jeanne d'Arc</u></b>; prompt on partial answer]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Biologist George Gaylord Simpson was a vehement opponent of this theory. Frank Taylor first proposed this theory in 1908, based on observing similarities in distant mountain ranges. This theory was picked up in 1912 by Alfred Wegener, who popularized it. For 10 points, identify this theory, ancestral to plate tectonics, which states that large land masses move over time.", "answer": "<b><u>continental drift</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>plate tectonics</u></b> until it is read]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "The planned city of Fatehpur Sikri (<b>pr. FAH-tay-poor SEE-kree</b>) was built as a capital in what is now this country. Several ancient empires in this present-day country were ruled from Pataliputra (<b>pr. puh-TAH-lee-POO-truh</b>). Edwin Lutyens designed this country's current capital across the Jammu River from the Red Fort. For 10 points, name this country governed from New Delhi.", "answer": "<b><u>India</u></b> [Republic of <b><u>India</u></b>] [or <b><u>Bharat</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In protest of this war, the \"Spot Resolutions\" were introduced by then-Congressman Abraham Lincoln. Another opponent of this war spent a night in jail after refusing to pay a poll tax that went to fund it. This war was stridently opposed by Henry David Thoreau and other transcendentalists as an extension of the slave power. For 10 points, name this war in which the battles of Veracruz, Cerro Gordo, and Chapultepec were fought against Santa Anna.", "answer": "<b><u>Mexican</u></b>-American War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This team\u2019s best defensive player of the 1970s missed the entire 1979 season in favor of professional boxing. This team, which employed Ed \u201cToo Tall\u201d Jones, defeated the Dolphins and Broncos to win two 1970s Super Bowls, and lost two more appearances, both to the Steelers. For 10 points, name this team of quarterback Roger Staubach and coach Tom Landry.", "answer": "<b><u>Dallas</u></b> Cowboys [or <b><u>Cowboys</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man won his first senate race over Robert La Follete Jr. He was challenged by Army counsel Joseph Welch during hearings where Roy Cohn assisted him. In a speech to the Republican Women's Club of Wheeling, West Virginia, he presented a list of names. For 10 points, name this Wisconsin Senator who instigated the early 1950s \"Red Scare\" in his hunt for Communists.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The man who won the 1970 election for this office was opposed in a coup known as the \"Tanquetazo\" (<b>pr. ton-kay-TOT-zoh</b>) and finally overthrown after nationalizing the copper industry, with the approval of Henry Kissinger and Richard Nixon. For 10 points, identify this office which Salvador Allende (<b>pr. eye-EN-day</b>) lost in a military coup led by Augusto Pinochet (<b>pr. pee-noh-CHAY</b>).", "answer": "<b><u>President of Chile</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This religion opposed the Nestorian heresy at the Council of Ephesus (<b>pr. EFF-uh-sis</b>) and advanced the doctrine of \"hypostasis\" (pr. <b>high-PAH-stuh-sis</b>) at the Council of Chalcedon. Earlier, this religion challenged the Arian movement at the Council of Nicaea (<b>pr. nigh-SEE-uh</b>). For 10 points, name this religion whose early ecumenical councils met under the supervision of the Pope.", "answer": "<b><u>Christian</u></b>ity [or Roman <b><u>Catholic</u></b>ism; or Eastern <b><u>Orthodox</u></b>y]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This goddess, who was born from the left eye of Izanagi (<b>pr. ee-zuh-NAH-gee</b>), is worshipped at a \"grand shrine\" that is torn down and rebuilt every twenty years. She is believed to be the ancestor of the \"tenno,\" who sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne. For 10 points, name this sun goddess, the sister of Susanowo, and the patroness of the Imperial house of Japan.", "answer": "<b><u>Amaterasu</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This company made the \"Kingsbury Commitment\" in 1913, agreeing to sell off its stake</u></b> <b><u>in Western Union. In 1984, this company again was brought up on (+)</u> antitrust charges, resulting in its fracturing into seven \"Baby (*)</b> Bells.\" For 10 points, name this company which formerly held a monopoly on U.S. telephone service and now is the second-largest wireless carrier.", "answer": "<b><u>AT&T</u></b> Corporation [or <b><u>American Telephone and Telegraph</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>Fossils of this species were first found in the Engis Caves of Belgium, though they get</u></b> <b><u>their name from subsequent finds on the outskirts of Dusseldorf in a namesake (+)</u> valley. This species was once believed to have been rendered extinct by bands of rock-throwing predators, though it is now known from DNA markers that they (*)</b> interbred with the ancestors of modern humans. For 10 points, name this large-skulled hominid which survived in Europe until 40,000 BC.", "answer": "<b><u>Neanderthal</u></b>s", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man was originally supposed to be the candidate of the Union Party in the 1936</u></b> <b><u>Presidential election. After his death, his brother (+)</u> Earl served three more terms on his platform. This politician proposed confiscating fortunes beyond a million dollars as part of his \"Share the Wealth\" plan, which he promoted with the slogan (*) </b>\"Every Man a King.\" For 10 points, name this \"Kingfish\" who was assassinated by Carl Weiss in 1935, ending his iron-fisted rule over Louisiana.", "answer": "Huey <b><u>Long</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Central Asian conquerors known as the Hepthalites are also called the \"white\"</u></b> <b><u>version of these people, who may also be identical to the Chinese (+)</u> Xiongnu (</b>pr. shong-NOO<b>). These people advanced into Western Europe shortly after the death of Bleda, and in 452, Pope Leo I negotiated a retreat of their forces from Rome.</b> (*) For 10 points, name these conquerors who briefly dominated Eastern Europe under the leadership of Attila.", "answer": "<b><u>Huns</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Tony Pastor and E.F. Albee were major producers of this form of entertainment. Ethnic</u></b> <b><u>versions of this entertainment genre included the Jewish \"Borscht Belt\" and the black</u></b> <b><u>\"Chitlin (+)</u> Circuit.\" This genre strictly prohibited anything offensive to \"family\" sensibilities and originally played many of thetheaters that were later converted to showing movies. (*) </b>For 10 points, identify this most popular form of entertainment in pre-1920 America, consisting of a series of stage acts.", "answer": "<b><u>Vaudeville</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this larger operation, soldiers were executed at Chenogne (</u></b><u>pr. chay-NON</u><b><u>) in</u></b> <b><u>revenge for the earlier Malmedy (</u></b><u>pr. mahl-may-DEE</u><b><u>) Massacre. Anthony McAuliffe issued</u></b> <b><u>the singular reply (+)</u> \"Nuts!\" to a surrender demand during this operation, which was named for the (*) </b>shape created in a map of troop lines in the Ardennes forest. For 10 points, name this late 1944 World War II initiative, the final major German offensive of the war.", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Bulge</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This organization set up a front called the Fairfield Foundation, through which it</u></b> <b><u>promoted what Nelson Rockefeller dubbed \"free enterprise painting.\" In response to</u></b> <b><u>Harry Truman's derision of modern art in 1947, this organization attempted to (+)</u> finance movements such as abstract expressionism in order to promote American cultural vitality against the stagnant (*)</b> socialist realism of the USSR. For 10 points, name this external spy agency of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>CIA</u></b> [or <b><u>Central Intelligence Agency</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Elbert Hubbard's inspirational story</u> </b><em><b><u>A Message to Garcia</u> </b></em><b><u>is set during this war. Mark</u></b> <b><u>Twain became a leader of the Anti-Imperialist League, which opposed this war. During this</u></b> <b><u>war, Frederic (+)</u> Remington worked as a photographer for William Randolph (*)</b> Hearst, who promised \"I'll furnish the war\" through his \"yellow journalism\" outlet, the <em>New York</em> <em>Journal</em>. For 10 points, name this war in which Cuba achieved independence and the U.S. annexed Puerto Rico.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish-American</u></b> War  <b>NHBB C 2014-201 </b> <b>Bowl Round 5 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras ONLY USE IF A BACKUP OR TIEBREAK IS NEEDED! </b> <b><u>A major terrorist group in this country absorbed the Socialist Patients' Collective, a group</u></b> <b><u>which believes that people with illnesses were the oppressed class in capitalist societies, and</u></b> <b><u>launched a 1977 campaign known as its \"autumn.\" This home of the (+)</u> Red Army Faction was also where members of (*)</b> Black September targeted athletes in 1972. For 10 points, name this country where terrorist incidents included the attack on Israelis at the Munich Olympics.  ANSWER: West <b><u>Germany</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}